<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Zak Soliman | Software Developer | Computer Scientist</title><link href="https://zaksoliman.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://zaksoliman.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://zaksoliman.com/</id><updated>2020-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Decided to Start Blogging. Why?</title><link href="https://zaksoliman.com/blog/blog/2020/introductions.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Zak Soliman</name></author><id>tag:zaksoliman.com,2020-02-09:/blog/blog/2020/introductions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After weeks (more like years) of thinking about starting blogging, of debating whether or not 
I have something interesting to contribute to this thing we call the world wide web, and of endlessly 
ruminating on why I should even start blogging, I've finally decided to just shut up and do …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After weeks (more like years) of thinking about starting blogging, of debating whether or not 
I have something interesting to contribute to this thing we call the world wide web, and of endlessly 
ruminating on why I should even start blogging, I've finally decided to just shut up and do it.
As by first post ever, I've decided to discuss the reasons that pushed me to finally start publishing my 
thoughts on the web in the hopes that this will help someone else going through the same hesitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Putting the Feynman Technique into Practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying the Feynman technique was the main motivator. The main idea is that if you have a deep understanding 
of some concept then you should be able to explain it to someone, that knows nothing about that particular 
subject, in an intuitive and easily understandable way. The technique is fairly simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading about a new concept, take a sheet of paper and write the name of the concept on the top of 
the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write down everything you know about the concept in plain english (no jargon, simple short words) as if 
you want to teach it to a total beginner in the field. Doing this will highlight the parts you don't fully 
understand. Take note of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go back to the literature and reviews the parts you don't yet master and repeat step 2 until satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Accountability&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all fine and dandy, but why do I need a blog to apply the Feynman technique. 
It's because I need to be accountable to someone in order to be sufficiently motivated to go through with 
the whole process. Maintaining a blog, although it most probably will not have a significant following at 
first (or maybe ever), is the perfect way to give myself a sense of obligation to consistently write new 
content to keep it fresh and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Productive Procrastination&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's be honest, most (all?) of us procrastinate, some more than others, but we do and I'm no different. 
Sometimes I procrastinate a lot, seriously, a LOT. In grad school, I often found myself wasting whole days 
because I had writers block for my thesis or I lacked inspiration for new experiments or analysis I could 
do. I noticed a pattern in my procrastination; I usually got lost in interesting TED or technology conference 
videos, articles about exciting new technologies from hacker news, and playing around with my side projects. 
Why not write a blog post about the new stuff I learn while procrastinating? What a great idea! Plus, I get 
the benefits of the Feynman technique discussed earlier. Everything is coming together nicely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Virtual (public) Notebook&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other very important benefit I get by writing blog posts about the stuff I learn about is that I have 
and archive of searchable and organized notes of all the things I learned that I can use for reference. 
This is by far preferable to my current method of having a ton of loose leafs all over my office with 
scribbles on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you are reading this and you find yourself, like me, in a fierce
internal debate on weather or not to start a blog, do it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog"></category></entry></feed>